# Yong Zhuang

📞 +1 (617)-763-8919 | 🔀 yong.zhuang001@umb.edu | 🛅 yong-zhuang-b1847a114 | 🗥 yong-zhuang.github.io

# **SUMMARY**

Graduated Ph.D. in Computer Science with a focus in applied machine learning seeking a role in Data Science / Machine Learning Engineering. Highly adept at feature selection, deep learning, and time series forecasting, but has a breadth of knowledge of data science techniques from work across various problem domains in industry and academia over the last seven years. During NSF Intern at Radial Analytics, Applied NLP and causal-based feature selection on clinical data to choose the most valuable features. Created deep neural networks to identify patient candidates across health levels with an average precision improvement of 17%. Have five years of software development experience leading a team of five before the Ph.D. study.

### **SKILLS**

Languages: Python, Java, ASP.NET, C#, PHP, JavaScript, HTML/CSS, SQL

Machine Learning Packages: Tensorflow, Keras, Pytorch, Matplotlib, Pandas, Numpy, scikit-learn, seaborn

Database: MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server, Access, Oracle

ArcGIS: Map, Server, SDE and Desktop

Developer tools: Git, Docker, VS Code, Visual Studio, Eclipse

Advanced Skills: Design Patterns, MVC, Jquery, AJAX

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Ph.D. Candidate, Research Assistant

Knowledge Discovery Lab

Dec. 2014 - Dec. 2021

Boston, MA, U.S.

Worked as a Ph.D. Candidate / Researcher in applied machine learning at the Knowledge Discovery Lab in UMBs Computer Science department, focusing on modeling real-world datasets using feature selection and deep neural networks in Python. Major work including:

- Created multi-Markov-blankets-based methods to identify precursors to heavy precipitation event clusters. Designed
  multi-Markov-blankets-based methods to identify precursors to heavy precipitation event clusters. Our method
  identified the cold surges along the coast of Asia as an essential precursor to the surface weather over the United
  States, a finding which climate experts later corroborated.
- Created a new recurrent neural network architecture (Error Trajectory Tracing) to track the trajectory of the prediction error through the phase space, and a new training regime (Horizon Forcing) to expand the prediction horizon of time series by more than 20%.
- Created Spatio-temporal deep neural networks improving crime hot Spot forecast F1-score by 21%.
- Supervised undergraduate lab assistants and mentored junior Ph.D. students in data science methodology and programming best practice.

#### **National Science Foundation Intern**

Jun. 2019 - Nov. 2019

Concord, MA, U.S.

Radial Analytics

- Applied natural language processing(NLP) and causal-based feature selection to clinical data to select the most valuable features related to patients' health status.
- Created deep neural networks to identify patient candidates across health levels with an average precision improvement of 17%.
- Designed an auto-machine-learning platform that automatically generates the best predictive model for given needs using feature selection and model selection.

## **Software Engineer**

Liaoning Triexcel Co., Ltd.

Mar. 2008 - Mar. 2013

Anshan, Liaoning, China

• Led front-end and back-end development of a GIS-based geological hazard management platform for data collection, data synchronism, risk scoring, and investigation planning.

- Led front-end and back-end development of an after-sales service management platform to rationalize the after-sale service process and Increase efficiency and customer satisfaction.
- Spearheaded product development of a remote solution to provide secure web remote control and system update services for terminals of Bank of Anshan.

# **PUBLICATIONS**

Zhuang, Y., Almeida, M., Ding, W., Flynn P., Islam, S., and Chen P., Widening the Time Horizon: Predicting the Long-Term Behavior of Chaotic Systems with Error-Trajectory Tracing and Horizon Forcing, Submitted to: IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI) [Under Revision]

Almeida, M., Zhuang, Y., Ding, W., Crouter, S. E., and Chen, P. (2021). Mitigating class-boundary label uncertainty to reduce both model bias and variance. ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from Data (TKDD), 15(2), 1-18.

Zhuang, Y., Small, D. L., Shu, X., Yu, K., Islam, S., and Ding, W. (2018, November). Galaxy: Towards Scalable and Interpretable Explanation on High-Dimensional and Spatio-Temporal Correlated Climate Data. In 2018 IEEE International Conference on Big Knowledge (ICBK) (pp. 146-153). IEEE.

Zhuang, Y., Almeida, M., Morabito, M., and Ding, W. (2017, August). Crime hot spot forecasting: A recurrent model with spatial and temporal information. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Big Knowledge (ICBK) (pp. 143-150). IEEE.

Zhuang, Y., Yu, K., Wang, D., and Ding, W. (2016, April). An evaluation of big data analytics in feature selection for long-lead extreme floods forecasting. In 2016 IEEE 13th International Conference on Networking, Sensing, and Control (ICNSC) (pp. 1-6). IEEE.

Zhuang, W. Y., and Ding, W. (2016, September). Long-lead prediction of extreme precipitation cluster via a spatiotemporal convolutional neural network. In Proceedings of the 6th International Workshop on Climate Informatics: CI.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Massachusetts Boston Ph.D, Applied Machine Learning, GPA 3.906 University of Massachusetts Boston MS, Computer Science, GPA 3.923	Sep. 2016 - Dec. 2021 Boston, MA, U.S. Sep. 2014 - Jun. 2016 Boston, MA, U.S.
HONORS and AWARDS	
Oracle Doctoral Research Fellowship Award The Collage of Science and Mathematics	Jun. 2016, 2018
The Randall Gates Malbone Fellowship The Collage of Science and Mathematics	May. 2019
National Science Foundation (NSF) Graduate Research Internship National Science Foundation	Jun. 2019
PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER	
SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD)	2022

2022

2019

2021, 2022

The SIAM International Conference on Data Mining (SDM)

The ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM)

AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligenceg (AAAI)